A biblical theology of generosity does not start with tithing, or even Jesus' command
to be generous to the poor.
It starts before time and space, with who God is.
Since the beginning of Scripture, the world itself was created as an act of generous love.
With God as a joyful, generous host, the world as His home, and you and I as His special guests.
And from the inner nature of God, giving becomes our nature.
And little by little, He makes our souls incandescent.
Well, good morning, church.
So good to be with you all this morning.
If we haven't had the privilege of meeting, which unfortunately I feel like it's more and more of us,
my name is Ryan.
I had the privilege of being one of the pastors here, and I would love to meet you if I have not yet done so.
If you're new or newer, we are in week four of a church-based curriculum, church-wide curriculum,
called Practicing the Way.
This is actually our third practice.
At the beginning of the year, we did prayer and fasting.
This year, we're doing generosity.
We'll do another three next year, and then another three the year after that.
And so we are finishing up generosity today.
The whole goal of the curriculum is aimed at helping us apply the lifestyle and teachings of Jesus
into our daily lives.
And I'm super thankful for all of you that have participated,
especially those of you that are participating in a small group.
It just adds so much more depth to the conversation.
You can have nuanced conversations with people that you trust about how to work these things out.
And so I'm excited about that.
Christ's teachings, I think you've probably noticed this last couple weeks on generosity,
they're countercultural, and they're often difficult to know how to contextualize,
how we should apply them specifically in our lives,
especially in the midst of a complex global economy
that often makes this idea of generosity even more challenging
than some of the other teachings of Jesus.
And so I personally just want to say to each one of you
how thankful I am to lead a church that is willing to take the example
and teachings of Jesus seriously, even when they're difficult,
and to put them into practice.
Just I was having a conversation with someone last night,
and they said, man, give me Romans, Galatians, Philippians,
give me all those books, and I got it.
You make me open up to the book of Luke,
and all of a sudden I'm like, what?
I have to do what?
We have to do what?
How is this?
You know, it just gets complicated.
The teachings of Jesus are challenging and complicated
and often feel overwhelming.
And oftentimes the American church has tried our best.
We've tried our best to explain away some of the hard teachings of Jesus.
We've tried to use some of the New Testament to reinterpret some of Jesus' words
so that we don't actually have to do what Jesus tells us to do.
And I'm just discontent with that approach.
So let's turn to Luke.
Why don't we?
It should be fun, right?
Luke chapter 12 is where we're going to end up here in just a few minutes.
This might be the longest introduction to any sermon that I've ever preached.
So maybe 20 minutes from now, we'll get to Luke chapter 12.
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, we are so grateful that you sent your son Jesus
to live a life demonstrating to us what true humanity looks like.
How life is supposed to be lived on earth as it is in heaven.
He lived a perfect life.
He demonstrated grace and sacrificial love.
And yet we crucified him.
And it was through his sacrificial death and resurrection
that he proved he was who he said he was.
And he has power in his teaching and in his life.
And therefore, everything he said is worthy to be trusted.
Everything he said will come true, will come to pass.
God, we have hope for the future because of the resurrection.
Remind us of that this morning.
Help us to have open hands with all of the possessions that you've given us
so that we can glorify you and serve our neighbor.
And it's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Do me a favor.
If you're in here and you would consider yourself an American football fan,
raise your hand.
Okay, good number of us.
Donovan made me say American football
because he said that it's actually not the real football.
Okay, so even if you're not a football fan,
raise your hand if you're going to watch the Super Bowl this year probably.
NFL Super Bowl, yeah, okay, cool.
Yep, all right, most of us.
And even if you're not even going to do that,
you've probably lived in America long enough
that you've been exposed to the rules, correct?
Most of us know the rules of football.
All right, well, just in case you don't know the rules,
I'm going to do a real high-level summary
because it's important that we're all on the same page for this.
We've got offense.
Offense tries to score points, right?
We've got defense.
Defense tries to stop,
and all of my football fans are like,
seriously, I have to sit through a one-on-one?
Don't worry.
All right, defense is trying to stop the team from scoring points.
We've got two levels of,
there's more than this,
but again, I said base level.
Two levels of scoring, right?
There's a touchdown,
which is worth six points,
and there's a field goal,
which is worth three points.
Now, imagine with me for just a second
that the week before the Super Bowl this year,
the commissioner comes out,
and he makes an announcement
that he has uncovered special historical documents
from the founding of the football league,
the American Football League,
and it turns out that we've been keeping score
the wrong way the entire time.
Apparently, the founders of the National Football League
or American Football,
they actually wanted to prioritize kicking field goals
rather than scoring touchdowns.
That's why when you watch the old black and white football films,
the field goal is actually at the front of the end zone.
That's why we call it football, right?
It seems weird to call a game football
that really isn't about kicking the football very often.
So the commissioner comes out.
He says, we've got new rules for the game.
We've been playing the game wrong the entire time.
This year's Super Bowl,
we will begin keeping score by the original rules.
And because this is America,
and we're all submissive
and love to unify around central concepts,
we would all be stoked.
No, right?
There's gonna be an uproar.
There's gonna be chaos.
Outrage from fans and the teams.
The teams have built their entire game plan
around scoring touchdowns rather than field goals.
Everything they've ever known,
they've been playing this game since childhood.
They've always been playing it
to prioritize touchdowns over field goals.
The fans, we don't wanna see a bunch of field goals, do we?
No.
We wanna see touchdowns.
That's crazy.
The stadium scorekeepers,
they have decided that they are gonna keep keeping score
by the rules that they know.
They don't want the commissioner
to impact the direction of the game at all.
Most likely, the fans will continue to cheer and or boo
based on the rules that they have watched played their entire life.
One team in the Super Bowl decides to ignore the commissioner's announcement.
They are gonna play the game the way that they've always played the game.
But the other team,
they're crazy enough to believe that the commissioner has the authority to make this decision.
They kick a field goal and let the other team score a touchdown.
They kick a field goal and they let the other team score a touchdown.
They're not even trying to stop them from scoring a touchdown.
The scoreboard is continuing to keep score based on the old rules
and the team that's trusting the commissioner.
It looks like they are losing.
It looks like everything is going wrong for them.
But the clock hit zero
and the confetti for the team that trusted the commissioner's word comes down.
He comes out and hands them the trophy.
They, in fact, are going to Disney World.
Right?
So, although this is a bit of a far-fetched scenario,
especially for the size and scope of what American NFL football has come to be,
but I think it's a helpful illustration.
For those of us that would consider ourselves followers of Jesus,
I think it illustrates for us the tension that we feel
as we seek to embrace the values of the kingdom of God
in a world that seems to be run by a totally different set of rules.
This is how the kingdom of God works.
The creator of the universe, the one who made the rules,
he steps into the playing field and he says,
we're playing by the wrong set of rules.
We're keeping score by the wrong metrics.
This is how life was intended to be.
Repent and follow me.
See, when God spoke the world into existence,
when he breathed the breath of life into the first humans,
it was good.
And there was order.
There was rules.
There was a plan.
But we rebelled.
We rejected his rules and his order
and decided to play our own game by our own set of rules.
Honestly, when you look at the Bible,
a quick Bible interpretation strategy here.
You see these pages right here?
This is the world as God intended it to be.
And then flip all the way to the back.
We'll go to the last like two or three pages.
See these pages?
Right, right.
That's too many.
Right here.
That's the world as God intended it to be.
This,
this is the tragedy of human rebellion.
This is God working his plan of redemption
in the midst of our brokenness and rebellion.
This is us playing our set of rules.
And yet,
those of us who have come to know and follow Jesus,
we trust that he has the authority.
We trust that his rules actually are the way to win.
The rest of the story is a tragedy
of the consequences of our rebellion
and God's effort to restore order to his creation.
And although this illustration will work
for every area of our lives,
because in every area of our lives,
we have rebelled
and we are keeping score
by a totally different set of rules,
whether it comes to all of our lives,
we are keeping score by a different set of rules.
But I think it works particularly well
when it comes to wealth, possessions, and finances.
See,
when it comes to our wealth and our possessions,
God set the world up to be run
by a specific set of rules.
We can see it very clearly
in the first page or two of Scripture.
And we can see it very clearly again
in the last page or two of Scripture.
God set the world
to be ruled by a certain set of rules.
He placed the first humans
in a luscious garden
that was being hydrated
by a river with four branches surrounding it.
The garden was full of raw potential,
enough resources
for all of humanity to share.
He invited Adam and Eve
to be fruitful and multiply,
to fill the earth and subdue it.
That was enough for everyone.
Raw potential,
opportunity for enough things
to be produced
for all of humanity to share,
for all of creation
to be taken care of.
Harness the raw potential
of God's creation
for his glory
and their neighbor's good.
This was the invitation
for Adam and Eve.
And yet Adam and Eve
and the rest of humanity
from that time forward,
we have doubted
that God's rules are good.
We took a bite of the tree
of the knowledge of good and evil.
We have redefined
what good looks like.
We've redefined
the rules of the game.
And now the rules of the game
when it comes to finances,
when it comes to possessions,
when it comes to wealth,
we have now said
that winning looks like
leveraging the raw potential
of God's creation
for our glory
and for the good of ourselves
and our people.
Right?
We hoard for ourselves.
We leverage the raw potential
of creation
in order to provide more for us,
even if it's at the expense
of others around us.
This is how the rules
of the game have shifted
from God's original intent
to what it looks like now.
And guess what the result is?
I just got a couple quick stats.
The top 20% of Americans
own 80% of the nation's wealth
and assets.
The top 1% of the world
owns close to 50%
of the world's assets.
We've changed the rules
of the game
and we're killing ourselves
and we're killing others
in order to win the game
while playing
by the wrong set of the rules.
Think about that.
1% of creation
owns 50%
of the world's assets.
God put Adam and Eve
in a luscious garden
with the raw potential
to be enough resources
for everyone to share
and we have rebelled
and we have taken
that resources,
we have taken those resources
and we have run away
from God
and we have separated
ourselves from one another
and now it's all about me
and mine
and what I can have
and what I can get.
And then,
this is the part
that really aggravates me
especially for people
that don't believe in God.
People who don't believe in God,
they look at populations
of starving individuals
and they blame God.
We're to blame.
There's more than enough resources
and yet we hoard for ourselves
rather than following God's rules
and sharing everything there is
and now you're like,
okay, Ryan,
now you just explained utopia.
That's wonderful and great
and how is that ever going to work?
I'm not a part of the top 1%.
What the heck am I supposed to do?
Okay, that's where
the illustration comes back in, right?
Like the kingdom of God
is an invitation
to join the team
that plays by the right set of rules.
The more of us
that are willing to believe
and trust that Jesus
is the creator of the universe
and that his rules
are the way to win
the more opportunity we have
to see the kingdom of God
built on earth
as it is in heaven.
This is the world
that Jesus steps into, right?
Jesus becomes flesh
in Rome
in the area ruled by Rome
and Rome were masters
of playing the wealth game
by the wrong rules.
They conquered massive territories
with land by military force,
exploiting entire groups
of people as slaves
and redistributing the wealth
to the ruling class
and the citizens of Rome.
This is the cultural backdrop.
The creator of the universe
takes on human flesh.
He steps into his creation.
He confronts the world
who is playing the game
by the wrong set of rules
on the field that he made.
He made the world.
He steps into the world.
We're playing the game
by the wrong set of rules
and this is where he announces
what he calls
the gospel of the kingdom of God.
The gospel is the creator
of the universe
inviting his creation
to begin to play the game
by his set of rules.
The gospel is recruiting
a new team of people
to play by the right rules.
And this is why
Scripture says
that the gospel
of the kingdom of God
is good news
for the poor.
Why would the gospel
be particularly good news
for the poor
and marginalized
if the gospel
is just about what happens
when we die?
Right?
We've kind of redefined
this word gospel
to mean the message of hope
for life after death
which it is that.
It is that
but it is so much
more than that.
The gospel isn't just
about where we go
when we die
but it's about
how we choose
to live now.
The gospel is Christ's invitation
to join a new team
and learn to play the game
by the proper rules
and this is why
it's good news
for the poor
because as more of us
choose to adopt
the creator's rule book
as more of us
join the team
who are willing to trust
that he has the authority
the more of us
that submit our lives
to his rule
and his reign
the more resources
we have
to be used
and leveraged
for his glory
and for the good
of others
and this will end up
being a net positive
for the poor
and marginalized.
Look at the early church.
There was no poor
among them.
They took the words
of Jesus seriously.
They sold everything
they had
and they brought it
all together
and I'm not arguing
that we do that right now
in that same way
but what I am arguing
is that Jesus
has the authority
to define the rules
of the game
and the more of us
who are willing
to submit our lives
to his rule
and his reign
the more resources
will get shared
and take care
of those
who are in need.
So,
that's the intro.
With the short amount
of time
I have left myself
I want to look
at Luke chapter 12
and I want to look
at three symptoms
that we might still
be playing
by the wrong set
of rules.
I think even
those of us
that would consider
ourselves
a follower of Jesus
myself
at the very top
of that list.
I agree with everything
that I just said
and yet far
more often than not
I find myself
playing by the rules
the culture's
rules of the game.
I was raised
in the American culture
with the American dream.
I have
this idea
is the foundation
of my world
and so often
I find myself
believing the teachings
of Jesus
that there's
more than enough
believing that
I can trust him
even when it looks
like there isn't
more than enough
believing that
I can trust him
even when I feel
like if I'm the only
one doing the right
thing how is this
ever going to work out
the scoreboard
seems to be stacked
against me
against us
as followers of Jesus
and yet
I trust him
and I find myself
not fully applying
his word properly.
So,
three symptoms
that we might
still be playing
by the wrong set
of rules
and then at the end
he's going to offer
Jesus is going to
offer generosity
to the poor
specifically to the poor
as a solution
to those three
symptoms.
If we take seriously
meeting the needs
of those who don't
have the basic
necessities for life
it can correct
some of the wrong
beliefs
and wrong rules
that we have
in our hearts
and our minds.
Does that sound
like a good plan?
I hope so
because that's
what we're doing.
Would you stand
with me?
I'm going to read
this passage
in Luke chapter 12
since I did
a 20 minute intro
I figured I'd
give you guys
a little bit
of exercise
in between.
Luke chapter 12
starting in verse 1
Meanwhile the crowds
grew until thousands
were milling about
and stepping on each other.
That's crazy.
Jesus turned first
to his disciples
and he warned them
beware of the yeast
of the Pharisees
their hypocrisy
the time is coming
when everything
that is covered up
will be revealed
and all that is secret
will be made known.
I started this passage
way too early.
Alright.
It's actually
verse 13
let's go back there
Luke chapter 12
verse 13
Then someone called
from the crowd
Teacher please
tell my brother
to divide
our father's estate
with me.
Jesus replied
Friend who made
me judge
over you
to decide
such things
as that?
Then he said
beware
guard against
every kind
of greed
life is not
measured
by how much
you own.
Hear a different
set of rules
than those
rules that
we've grown up
with.
Then he told
them a story
a rich man
had a fertile
farm that
produced fine
crops.
He said to
himself
what should
I do?
I don't have
enough room
for all my
crops.
Then he said
I know
I'll tear
down my
barns
and I'll
build bigger
ones.
Then I'll
have room
enough to
store all
the wheat
and my
other goods.
I'll sit
back and
I'll say
to myself
friend
you have
enough
stored away
for years
to come
now take
it easy
eat
drink
and be
merry.
But God
said to him
you fool
you will die
this very
night.
Then who
will get
everything
that you
worked
for?
Yes a
person is a
fool to
store up
earthly wealth
but not have
a rich
relationship
with God.
Jump down
to verse
33.
Jesus says
therefore sell
your possessions
give to those
in need.
This will store
up a treasure
for you in
heaven and
the persons
of heaven
never get
old or
develop
holes.
Your
treasures
will be
safe.
No thief
can steal it.
No moth
can destroy it.
Wherever
your treasure
is there
are the
desires
of your
heart
will also
be.
This is
the word
of the
Lord.
We're
getting there.
You guys
can have
a seat.
Do we
feel the
tension
in this
story of
the rules
that we've
grown up
believing in
our culture
and in
our world?
This guy
this rich
fool
as my
Bible
likes to
call him
this rich
fool
is doing
what most
of us
have been
taught
is the
right way
to handle
your
finances.
Right?
Get
enough
for you
and your
family.
Store
and make
plans
and prepare
for the
future.
These are
things which
is why we
wrestle with
Jesus' words.
Right?
We had that
conversation at
the beginning.
This is crazy.
Some of this
stuff is crazy.
But it's not
crazy if he
created the
universe and
has the
authority to
tell us how
to do what
we need to
do with his
stuff.
In our
story today,
Jesus responds
to a young
man asking a
question about
money and
possessions.
And he
responds with
a parable
that might
seem slightly
disconnected
from the
question that
was asked,
but he's
Jesus,
so guess
what?
It's not.
And we'll
see this
different set
of rules.
So,
first symptom
that we
might be
playing by
the wrong
set of
rules
is the
symptom of
entitlement.
Entitlement.
This individual
asked Jesus,
We can
see very
clearly that
this individual
has an
entitlement
idea.
That
inheritance is
mine.
I deserve
it.
at least a
portion of
it.
My brother
might have
been given
it by my
father legally,
but I
deserve a
portion of
the inheritance.
I need
that money.
That money
belongs to
me.
He believes
it's his
money.
He believes
that he
deserves it
and that
anyone who
gets in
the way
of him
is wrong.
And
entitlement
is a
symptom that
we are
playing by
the wrong
set of
rules.
We often
get sucked
into believing
that we
deserve more
than we
need.
After all,
we've worked
hard,
we've made
good decisions
and therefore
we deserve
a certain
level of
financial gain.
We have
this spirit
of entitlement,
the darkest
version of
the spirit
of entitlement
that many
of us
might not
verbalize out
loud when
anybody's
around,
but we
believe and
say in
our hearts,
I played
the game
better than
those people
who are in
need.
It's not
my fault
they're
struggling.
They should
have worked
harder.
They should
have made
better decisions.
At the end
of the day,
we can
summarize that
with a very
famous saying
from Genesis,
am I my
brother's keeper?
the culture
feeds us
this idea
of entitlement,
we deserve
all that
we have.
And what's
crazy is you
think about
an inheritance,
right?
The definition
of inheritance
is you didn't
do anything
to earn it.
The definition
of inheritance
is your parents
did the work
to earn the
inheritance and
the son is
saying that's
mine, I
deserve it,
it belongs
to me.
And that
is what
we do
when we
look at
God who
is the
giver of
every good
gift that
we have
and we
say this
is mine.
I've worked
hard for
this, I've
made good
decisions, I've
leveraged my
skills and
my resources
and this
is mine, I
deserve it.
The competing
kingdom rule of
entitlement is
stewardship, this
is what Nick
covered last
week, I'm not
going to go
super deep into
it because we
had a whole
message last
week, but
stewardship
flips the
script from
I deserve
this to God
gave this to
me as a
gift.
And I
think the
reason that
Jesus offers
regularly giving
to the poor
as a solution
to entitlement
is because when
we regularly and
sacrificially give
to those in
need, it
reminds us that
everything we
have is a
gift from God
when we were
in need.
Everything we
have, the
breath in your
lungs, the
relationships and
resources that you
have because of
the family that
you were born
in, you did
not choose to
be born into
that family.
It was a
gift from
God.
Everything that
we have is a
gift from
God.
And when we
generously give to
those who don't
have enough, it
reminds us that
everything we have
is a gift from
God that we
don't deserve.
Entitlement is a
symptom that we're
playing by the
wrong rules of the
game.
And I don't know
about you, but I
struggle with
entitlement almost
every day.
Right?
Like I, I
surrendered my
life to ministry
when I was 16
years old.
I did the
thing that like
nobody wants to
do, right?
I'm a pastor and
I often find
myself, the evil
parts of my heart
creep in and say,
you're doing this
for the Lord.
But what's crazy is
that if you're in
here and you're a
follower of Jesus,
what you're doing is
for the Lord.
You're physical
therapy for the
Lord.
You're accounting
for the Lord.
You're doing
every, all of us
that are surrendered
to the life of
Jesus, we're all
doing what we're
doing for the
Lord.
We're leveraging
our skills and
our resources to
build his kingdom
on earth as it is
in heaven.
And so entitlement
has no place for
those of us who are
followers of Jesus
because everything we
have is a gift.
So this week, this
month, this might be
a long process, this
whole generosity
thing.
We might be, we
might be picking up
the pieces from the
bomb that I have
exploded in our
community of people
for a while.
But what I want you
to think about over
the next few weeks
and months as
you're looking at
your finances, as
you're thinking about
how you use your
money is where
might entitlement
be creeping into
my heart?
Where might I feel
like I deserve more
than I need?
Where might I feel
like I have
leveraged all of
the, I've made the
right decisions, I
deserve this?
And how might
sacrificially giving
to the poor be a
solution to that
problem in your
heart?
All right, symptom
number two.
First is
entitlement.
Jesus then goes on
to tell a parable
that seems like it's
somewhat disconnected,
but it really isn't,
about a rich man.
He had a fertile
farm, produced fine
crops.
He said to himself,
what should I do?
I don't have room for
all my crops.
I know, I'll tear down
my barns and I'll build
bigger ones.
Then I'll have room
enough to store up all
the wheat and other
goods.
I'll sit back and I'll
say to myself, my
friend, you have enough
stored away for years
to come.
I think the reason
Jesus shares this
parable as a response
to this man's
question is because
entitlement often leads
to the next two
symptoms that we find
in this passage.
Entitlement often
leads to us saving
far more than we
need and leveraging
our wealth for
earthly pleasures.
Saving more than we
need, spending more
than we need, that
comes directly out of
this heart of
entitlement.
The rich man in the
parable, he believes
that his excess is a
result of him winning
at the game.
So he decides to
store up way more
than he needs while
others around him
don't have enough
to live.
Now, some of you
get nervous.
I'm getting nervous,
don't worry.
There's tension here,
right?
Am I the only one
that feels the
tension here?
This came up a
couple weeks ago in
our small group as
we were diving into
this topic and
somebody blurted
out at the end of
small group, which I
love.
That's what I love
about small group
is that we trust
each other enough to
say what we're
actually thinking.
Somebody blurted
out, okay, I guess
whenever I give my
401k, I'm a
sinner.
And then everybody
kind of like chuckled
and looked at me
awkwardly.
Right?
I love that.
This conversation is
important.
I want to be
careful here because
there's a tension in
Scripture between
making wise plans for
the future and
giving freely and
generously to those
in need with no
worry about the
future.
Right?
This is the part
we skipped.
The whole chunk of
Scripture that we
skipped is Jesus
saying don't worry
about the future.
God's going to
take care of you.
And so there is
this tension that
God will take care
of us and yet
there's a tension
that we need to
make wise plans.
And so all I
want to do
pastorally here is
say that just
because there's
a tension doesn't
give us permission
to ignore it
altogether.
It doesn't mean
that we just keep
doing things the
way that we've
always been doing
things.
We keep investing
the same percentage
or a growing
percentage in our
future retirement
account without
thinking about the
needs, the basic
necessities of those
around me.
we've got to
shift the question
from how much
can I save so
that I can have a
lavish retirement to
how much is too
much.
And again, I've
said this throughout
the series, I
cannot answer this
question for you.
Every one of us will
answer this question
differently but I
invite you to ask the
Holy Spirit in prayer
to look at your
finances, to make a
plan for how much
you should save and
how much you should
give generously to
those who are in
need and ask for
feedback from people
that you trust.
Regularly giving to
the poor helps us put
this question into
perspective.
The person in your
community who doesn't
have the basic
necessities for today
is just as valuable,
has just as much
dignity and worth as
you do in the
future.
In the future, you
might not even exist.
None of us are
promised tomorrow.
So we've just got to
put this tension into
perspective.
We've just got to
invite the Holy Spirit
to give us wisdom
about this.
Marissa and I are
doing this right now.
It's a very
challenging thing.
We had a meeting
with a financial
planner and he gave
me a percentage of
how much money that
we should be
investing in our
future retirement.
And it was a big
percentage.
And Marissa and I
are going to have
to wrestle with
that question.
We're going to
have to figure out
that question for
ourselves.
We're going to
have to ask the
Holy Spirit, how
much is enough to
save and how much
can we leverage now
for generosity to
those who are in
need?
And I do not have
this figured out.
I'm not up here
telling you that I
have figured it
out.
I am just relaying
to you this parable
from Jesus and
trying to flush out
what we should be
doing with it, even
in the tension.
Regularly giving to
the poor puts this
question into
perspective.
It reminds me of
Jesus' words in
Matthew chapter 25.
He says,
whatever you do for
the least of these,
you did for me.
The creator of the
universe is reminding
us that each
individual is an
image bearer of
God.
Every single human
being is created in
the image of God
and is worthy, is
valuable, has
dignity, respect.
Even if they've
made bad decisions,
even if they find
themselves in a
difficult place, our
responsibility is to
make sure that every
human being that we
are in contact with
has the basic
necessities of life.
And we can't solve
that problem by
ourselves.
We've got to do it
together and work
with the Holy Spirit.
Okay, heavy stuff.
Are we good?
We're alive?
Okay.
Symptom number three.
Why does this man
decide to save up far
more than he needs?
Well, that leads us to
symptom three.
He seeks temporary
pleasure through wealth
and possessions.
I'll sit back and I'll
say to myself, my
friend, you have
stored away for more
than you need for
years to come.
now take it easy,
eat, drink, and be
merry.
But God said to him,
you fool, you will
die this very night.
Then who will get
everything that you
worked for?
See, the motivation
for this man storing
up way more than he
needs was so that he
could spend more than
he needs on the
fleeting pleasures of
this life.
This phrase, eat,
drink, and be merry,
the Jews in the
audience would have
immediately hyperlinked
to the book of
Ecclesiastes.
Those of you that
have been around the
Bible long enough
know the book of
Ecclesiastes.
If you don't, the
book of Ecclesiastes
is King Solomon
doing a social
experiment with his
massive wealth and
possessions.
He tries out every
potential hobby,
every potential thing
he could ever do
with more money than
you or I will ever
have.
And at the end of
it, he tells the
people of Israel
that it's all
fleeting, that there's
no satisfaction under
the sun, that
earthly pleasures
will never satisfy
your eternal soul.
And so the response
then either is to
live for the future,
live for the
resurrection, live
for eternity, or if
you totally reject
that idea, Solomon
says, all right,
fine, then just eat,
drink, and be merry.
Right?
Just live it up.
Squander all of your
wealth and your
possessions and do
whatever you can to
find satisfaction on
earth because there's
nothing after this
life.
That is the tension
that we wrestle with.
And I am just crazy
enough to believe
Solomon and Jesus
that there is nothing
about temporary
pleasure that will
satisfy my soul.
It doesn't mean that
temporary pleasures
aren't good.
It doesn't mean that
we won't find
enjoyment in them.
It just means at the
end of the day, they
over-promise and
under-deliver.
And giving generously
to the poor helps
us put our luxury
spending into the
proper perspective.
When we're regularly
in relationship with
people who don't have
the basic necessities
for life, it changes
the question from can
I afford this to
should I buy this?
And I'm not going to
answer that question
for you.
I have a hard enough
time answering it
for myself.
It causes us to ask
counter-cultural
questions like how much
is enough?
What luxury should I
forego in order to
help provide the
basic necessity of
those who don't
have enough?
Again, back to
small group.
I love small groups.
You're going to hear
it a lot.
It's fine.
The next week, after
the, we're sending
for donating, or for
investing in our Roth
IRA, we were kind of
teasing around some of
these ideas.
And another person in
our small group said,
person in our small
group said, okay,
every time I have
Starbucks, I'm
sending.
I'm like, I love this
so much.
We're having a lot of
fun.
Everybody awkwardly
chuckles and looks
at me.
That's the only part I
don't like about being
in a small group is
that I'm not supposed
to be the pastor in
small group, and we
do a pretty good job
of it, but when
something awkward
comes up, it's like,
Ryan's going to have
to answer this one.
Right?
And what I want to
say to that is that
we can easily fall
into the trap of
guilt and shame.
We can easily
pendulum swing.
say, man, every
little thing that I
ever get is not
something that I
need.
Therefore, I'm
sending, and
therefore, yes,
conviction.
Exactly.
And so what I'm
going to say to
her, what I said to
her is like, you've
got to answer that
question for yourself.
Maybe going to
Starbucks ten times
less a month and
investing that money
in people who don't
have the basic
necessities of life,
maybe that's what
God's calling you to
do.
I'm not going to
answer that question
for you.
I know.
I'm using a lot of
cop-outs, and I'm
making my job far
easier than it
should be, but
again, ask the
Lord what he would
have you to do.
We can easily fall
into this trap of
guilt and shame.
That's not the
purpose of Christ's
invitation.
Christ's invitation
is to consider where
the abundant life is
truly found, to take
intentional steps to
invest your resources
in what will truly
satisfy you and will
have lasting long-term
impact.
This is a lifelong
process that we're
never going to get
right all the time.
My mom will probably
love that I share
this story.
When I was in high
school, I decided to
read a book by
Francis Chan called
Crazy Love, and
Francis Chan pretty
much took Jesus'
words and made them
modern for me, and I
felt like I wasn't
even a Christian by
the time I finished
that book.
Anybody read that
book and felt the
same way?
Some of us.
That's great.
So 16-year-old me
decided to get rid of
every single piece of
clothing my parents
had ever bought me,
and I had seven
t-shirts, and I only
wore seven t-shirts,
and I big sharpie
marketed them because
I wanted to be an
evangelist to my high
school friends, and I
was like, hey, look.
They're like, why do
you have a t-shirt with
a big number three on
it?
I'm like, because I
only have seven shirts
because Jesus wants us
to take care of the
poor, right?
Like, I was a blast in
high school.
Everybody loved hanging
out with me.
So I share that story
to say, like, invite the
Holy Spirit, allow
conviction to lead you
into the right place.
Don't swing the
pendulum, but if God's
calling you to swing
the pendulum, that's
where you've got to
decide for yourself.
Where is the Holy
Spirit leading us?
Don't be led by guilt
and shame.
Be invited into the
true abundant life that
Jesus has for us.
Kelly, if you want to
come up, I'm going to
start wrapping up.
That'd be great.
We had a conversation
in our meeting.
I usually try and give
her a subtle cue, and
that never ends up
working out as well as
I'd like it to.
So the subtle cue has
been removed.
Okay, so Jesus, he
tells this parable.
He talks about not
worrying about the
future, and then he
ends with this idea of
giving to the poor as a
solution to the problem
in the heart of the
individual asking about
the inheritance and in
the heart of the fake
person in the parable
story.
Sell all your
possessions.
Give to those in
need.
This will store up a
treasure for you in
heaven.
And the purses of
heaven never get old
or develop holes.
Your treasures will be
safe.
No thief can steal it.
No moth can destroy
it.
Wherever your treasure is,
there the desires of
your heart will also be.
I realize that for most
of us, this practice is
going to be very
challenging and
overwhelming.
I have felt the
tension myself.
Honestly, the thing
that's been most
impactful for me is
that question of, do
I, can I afford this
and do I need this?
Because I don't, I
don't have a ton of
expendable income, but
I have some.
And when I go, when I
look at how much I'm
being generous, I'm
like, okay, well,
that's really all I can
be generous for.
But now, as I'm
interacting with the
teachings of Jesus, as
I'm thinking about
this, now I go to buy
something that I can't
afford, and I'm
asking myself, I need
this, can I
leverage this $3, $6, $9,
whatever it is, can I
leverage this to help
others in need?
Most of us, we've
built our lives, building
our budget by the world
set of rules, rather
than the kingdom of
God.
We've been trying to
score touchdowns.
When all along, we
were trying to, we're
supposed to make field
goals, who knew?
We've either built our
budgets on the world
set of rules, or this
Christian variation,
where we give God 10%
up front, and then the
other 90% we use
according to the
culture's rules.
So my invitation, for
those of us that want to
take seriously the
teachings of Jesus, that
want to demonstrate the
kingdom of God on earth
as it is in heaven,
consider updating your
budgets according to the
principles of the
kingdom of God.
This might be hard.
It might feel like a
football coach who spent
their entire life building
plays to score
touchdowns, and now you
have to retrain yourself
all together.
It also might feel like the
vast majority of people
around you are playing by a
different set of rules, and
you might feel like you're
actually losing, even when
we're winning.
Helping the poor can feel
like a losing battle.
There's so many people in
need, and you only have a
small amount to share.
Where do you start?
Who do I give to?
How much do I give to
them?
How is this going to work
out?
How is this going to make a
difference at all?
I share a stat, like 1% of
the world owns 50% of the
resources, and you might feel
crippled or paralyzed, and
like your little extra amount
is not going to make a
difference.
And I just want to think
about the little boy with a
few fish and a few loaves.
The Lord will multiply your
obedience.
faithfulness.
What little you can have to
offer will do so much more
than you can ever imagine.
Prioritize relationships.
Get in relationships.
If you're not in
relationships with people who
don't have basic necessities
for life, find a way.
They're all over Frederick
County.
Find a way to build
relationships with a few
people that you can give both
resources and support and
encouragement and prayer to.
What if people I give to make
bad decisions with the money
that I give?
That's a tough one, right?
We talked in our staff a little
bit this week about what about
panhandlers, right?
What do we do with those people?
And April shared, I hope she, I
just doxxed her, so now we're in
trouble.
I hope she doesn't mind me
sharing this story.
I should have asked April if
you're here.
I'm so sorry.
She was like, hey, like most of
the time I don't because there's
a lot of potential risk and
challenge there.
But like sometimes I feel really
clearly led that the Holy
Spirit wants me to do something
for that person.
And that's where I just don't
want to have hard and fast
rules, right?
All of this is about inviting
the Holy Spirit to give you
direction about how you can
leverage your resources for the
good of others and for the
glory of God.
I also realize that there are
some of us in the room who do
not have enough money to save
for our future and we are not
spending on luxuries.
Christ's invitation to you is to
view everything that you have,
what little you have, as a gift
from God for his kingdom.
Invite the Holy Spirit to show
you how you can be generous with
your time, with your resources,
with your relationships.
And for you joyfully, be
willing to joyfully receive
other people's generosity.
Don't be proud or feel guilty
or shame.
Everything, everything on earth
is a gift from God.
And if somebody feels led to
give you something, to bless you
with something, receive it with
thanksgiving.
Again, this looks vastly different
for each of us.
My challenge for you is to sit
down, invite the Holy Spirit to
give you direction and make a
plan for your finances and
resources according to the rules
of the kingdom of God.
Some of you already have a very
solid plan.
Some of you have a very clear
budget, you know where every
single one of your dollars and
cents goes.
That's awesome.
Just reevaluate.
Is it going to the places that
you want it to go?
Jesus wants it to go?
Others of us have a little plan
or no plan at all.
Make one.
You'll be surprised to find out
where all of your money and
resources are going.
First and I, again, pendulum
person.
Sometimes I got a great budget.
I know where every dollar and
cents going.
Other times I have no budget.
I'm usually somewhere in the
middle where it's kind of like
this iffy budget.
And this series has been
challenging me to find where
every dollar is going and ask
the Holy Spirit, am I
comfortable with that direction
of my finances?
Do I feel like I'm investing in
the kingdom of God?
Ask God to reveal where a
spirit of entitlement might be
present in your finances.
Are you saving the right
amount or too much?
Are you spending the right
How might you be able to
leverage your resources to
help those who don't have the
basic necessities for life?
Finally, maybe here you feel
like this whole series is a bit
much.
After all, who am I to stand up
here and lecture you about what
to do with your money?
Maybe you're in here and you're
not really sure about this
whole Jesus thing.
You're just kicking the tires of
Christianity and you're like,
if this is what Christianity is
like, I don't know that I'm
interested.
I want to say to you that
generosity is at the heart of
the gospel.
I think I said this last week,
the reason so many of us in
here are willing to sit and
listen to me lecture about how
to spend money is because we've
had a radical encounter with
Jesus.
We believe that he's the
creator of the universe.
We've seen his sacrificial
love on the cross and therefore
everything we have is his.
Our life is his.
1 John 3, 16 through 18 says,
this is how we know what love
is.
Jesus Christ laid down his life
for us and we also ought to lay
down our lives for our brothers
and sisters.
Generosity is at the heart of the
gospel.
We don't give freely if we
haven't had a radical encounter
with Jesus.
But once we've had a radical
encounter with Jesus, everything
changes.
He goes on, if anyone has
material possessions and sees a
brother or sister in need but has
no pity on them, how can the love
of God be in that person?
Dear children, let us not love
with words or speech but with
actions and in truth.
So if you're in here and you're
not a follower of Jesus, I just
want to share with you that this
is the heart of the gospel.
The creator of the universe
stepped down from heaven into his
creation in order to show us that
we're playing the game by the wrong
step of the rules.
He laid down his life so that we
might have life.
He invites us to follow his
example.
The gospel is so much more about
where we go when we die.
It is that.
The gospel is about the creator of
the universe inviting us to live
according to his rules, his reign.
If you've never experienced the
love of Christ, you will likely
have little motivation to
sacrificially give out of your
excess.
However, once you've experienced
the sacrificial love of Christ,
you can't help but follow his
example.
If you're in that boat, this
whole thing's a bit perplexing
to you.
We have a prayer tent over here.
If you want to ask more questions
about Jesus, who he is, what he
did, we'd love to have a
conversation with you.
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, you are a
generous God.
You give freely and generously to
us, and you invite us to share in
your generosity with others.
God, may we get a vision for your
kingdom on earth as it is in
heaven.
May we hold our finances with an
open hand.
May we allow the Holy Spirit to
lead us.
And God, may you multiply exceedingly
abundantly more than we could ever
ask, think, or imagine with the
little bit of resources that we
have.
May you multiply them as we seek to
meet the needs of others.
For your glory and for our good.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
Stand with me.
Let me read the final
benediction over you for this
series.
And if you are in here and you're
a volunteer, I'm really bummed about
the weather.
I promise we're going to have a good
time tonight.
We'd love to have you here for 530
for that event.
It's going to be a great time.
Okay.
May God bless you abundantly so that
in all things, at all times, you may
have all that you need.
May you freely scatter your gifts to
the poor.
May God who supplies seed to the sower
and bread for food also supply and
increase your store of seed and
enlarge the harvest of your
righteousness.
May you be enriched in every way so
that you can be generous on every
occasion.
And may your generosity result in
thanksgiving to God.
Amen.
Go in peace, church.